Charles Brooks Papers
Charles Brooks Papers
1960-1969
1965-1969
Brooks, Charles G., 1920-
1.8 linear ft.
126 original editorial cartoons, correspondence and clippings.
148868
Biographical History
Charles G. Brooks (1920- ) is an American editorial cartoonist who worked for the Birmingham News for 38 years.
Charles Brooks was born in Andalusia, Alabama on November 20, 1920. He studied at Birmingham-South College starting in 1939. Wanting to focus on cartooning, he left for the Chicago Academy of Fine Arts in 1941 where he studied under Pulitzer Prize winning cartoonist Vaughn Shoemaker.
Brooks enlisted in the Army and saw combat during World War II. Following his service, Brooks worked in Chicago producing cartoons for an advertising agency. In 1948, Brooks became the Birmingham News’ first editorial cartoonist. In the mid 1980s, Brooks retired from the Birmingham News.
Thirteen Freedom Foundation awards were presented to Brooks as well as a National VFW Award and a Sigma Delta Chi Award (1960). Brooks was president of the American Association of Editorial Cartoonists and in 1968 he was the president of the Alabama Chapter of the Sigma Delta Chi Journalism Fraternity. Brooks’ cartoons have been exhibited at the Birmingham Public Library, the National Portrait Gallery in London, and the Smithsonian.
Brooks edits the annual compilation Best Editorial Cartoons of the Year which was first published in 1973 and is a member of the American Association of Editorial Cartoonists.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Charles Brooks Papers consist of consists of 2 series. The first series, Cartoons (1965-1969) contains 126 original, dated cartoons from Brooks' tenure at the Birmingham News. Brooks often portrayed the Southern point of view on national issues however few of the cartoons in this particular collection focus on specific Birmingham or Alabama issues. The Vietnam War and issues related to civil unrest dominated Brooks' subject matter during this time. The cartoons were drawn on illustration board primarily with ink and graphite.
The second series is Correspondence and Newspaper Clippings which contains 8 pieces of correspondence (1964-1967) sent to Brooks and 3 newspaper clippings (1960, 1967).
Arrangement of the Collection
Cartoons are arranged in chronological order. Correspondence and clippings are arranged as received.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Birmingham news.; Brooks, Charles G., 1920-; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- Alabama.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Political cartoons.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Charles Brooks, 1967-1970.
Inventory
- Cartoons, 126 items 13" x 19 1/4"; Click here for a list of specific dates.; See below for an index to the cartoons.
  - 1965 (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
  - 1966 (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
  - 1967 Jan, Apr (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
  - 1967 May (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
  - 1967 Jun-Jul (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
  - 1967 Aug-Oct (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
  - 1967 Nov-Dec (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
  - 1968 Jan-Feb (Oversize 2, Folder 1)
  - 1968 Mar-Apr (Oversize 2, Folder 2)
  - 1968 May-Jun (Oversize 2, Folder 3)
  - 1968 Jul-Aug (Oversize 2, Folder 4)
  - 1968 Sep-Dec (Oversize 2, Folder 5)
  - 1969 Jan-Apr, Jun (Oversize 2, Folder 6)
  - 1969 Aug-Oct (Oversize 2, Folder 7)
  - 1969 Nov-Dec (Oversize 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence and newspaper clippings
  - Incoming correspondence, 1964-1967; undated (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - "Sketchbook by Brooks- EXPO 67", 14 May 1967 (Box 1)
    - "George Wallace: Candidate for President", 21 May 1967; transcript of a question and answer session at which Brooks participated (Box 1)
    - "News cartoonist wins SDX award", 18 Apr 1960 (Box 1)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
Britain B2F1-B2F2 B2F6
Brown, H. Rap B2F1
California B1F4 B2F3
Canada B1F5
capital punishment B2F3
Carmichael, Stokely B1F5 B2F1
China B1F2 B1F4 B1F6
cities B2F8
civil rights B1F5
Clark, Ramsey B2F2 B2F4
college students B2F6
communism B1F4 B1F6 B2F1 B2F3-B2F4 B2F8
Congress B1F2-B1F4 B1F6-B1F7 B2F2
crime B1F4 B2F1 B2F6
Czechoslovakia B1F5 B2F4 B2F7
de Gaulle, Charles B1F2 B1F5 B1F7 B2F4 B2F6
Democratic National Convention B2F4
Democratic Party B2F4
demonstrations B1F6 B2F2 B2F4 B2F6-B2F8
Dominican Republic B1F2
draft B1F1 B2F1 B2F3
Egypt B1F4 B2F7
ethics code B1F4 B2F2
Fortas, Abe B2F4
France B1F5 B1F7 B2F5-B2F6
free press B2F1
Fulbright, J. William B1F2 B2F1
Germany B1F5 B2F6
Gore, Albert B2F8
Great Society B1F2 B1F6
Ho Chi Minh B1F4 B1F6 B2F5-B2F6
Humphrey, Hubert B1F2 B2F5
Hungary B1F5
inflation B1F7 B2F8
Israel B1F4-B1F5
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B1F2 B1F5 B1F7-B2F1 B2F3-B2F4 B2F6
Kennedy, Robert F. B1F2 B2F2-B2F3
Kennedy, Ted B2F8
King Jr., Martin Luther B1F5
Kosygin, Alexey B1F5
Latin America B1F6
Lodge Jr., Henry Cabot B2F6 B2F8
Mansfield, Michael B1F4
McCarthy, Eugene B1F7 B2F4
McNamara, Robert B2F1
Middle East B1F4-B1F5 B2F7
military B2F7-B2F8
Mills, Wilbur B2F3
Morse, Wayne B1F2
Morton, Sen. B1F6
Nixon, Richard M. B2F2-B2F3 B2F6-B2F8
nuclear weapons B2F4
Papacy B2F7
peace B1F6 B2F1 B2F3-B2F8
Pearson, Lester B. B1F5
Poland B1F5
Pompidou, Georges B2F4 B2F6
prices B1F2 B1F6
Republican Party B2F1
Reuther, Walter B1F6
Rhodesia B2F2
riots B1F5-B1F6
Rockefeller, Nelson B2F2-B2F3
Romania B1F5
Romney, George W. B1F6 B2F1
Rusk, Dean B2F1
Russia B1F6 B2F4 B2F6-B2F7
smut B2F7
Soviet Union B1F5 B2F4
space exploration B1F2-B1F3 B1F6-B1F7 B2F7-B2F8
strikes B1F2
Supreme Court B1F4-B1F5 B1F7 B2F3
taxes B1F6 B2F1-B2F3 B2F6-B2F8
Thant, U. B1F4 B2F2 B2F5
U.S. dollar B1F7 B2F2 B2F5
United Arab Republic B1F4
United Nations B1F5 B2F8
USS Pueblo B2F1 B2F5
Vietnam War B1F1-B2F8
Wallace, George B2F2
Wilson, Harold B2F1